A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Office Files of David Bonbright FA710
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Office Files of David Bonbright
1979-1987
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA710
3.6 Cubic Feet
The Office Files of David Bonbright, Assistant Program Officer (1983-1986) and Program Officer (1986-1987) of the Ford Foundation's Developing Country Programs (DCP), document his oversight of grantmaking and administration of field offices throughout Africa, with an emphasis on his work in developing a Foundation portfolio in South Africa. The collection spans 1979-1987 and consists of correspondence and subject files. The records were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1991, and were fully processed in 2006. The arrangement of the collection follows the original order established by David Bonbright.
Conditions Governing Access
Material is open for scholarly research, with prior archival review.
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Biographical note
David Bonbright was Assistant Program Officer (1983-1985) and Program Officer (1986-1987) of the Ford Foundation's Developing Country Programs. His areas of responsibility were South Africa, regional African grants, and New York support for African field offices. With DCP Vice President William Carmichael, Bonbright represented the Foundation at meetings of the Study Group on Southern Africa, a committee of foundation and university executives convened by the Carnegie Corporation to promote better educational opportunities for black South Africans.
Organizational history
The administration of Ford Foundation international programs was restructured in 1980-1981, and a new office for Developing Country Programs (DCP) was created. DCP coordinated the work of Foundation field offices overseas, and of New York-based staff responsible for grants to developing countries. David Bonbright oversaw DCP work throughout Africa during 1983-1987, and played a key role in the development of the Foundation’s South Africa portfolio.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of David Bonbright document Developing Country Program grantmaking and program administration throughout Africa during the period 1979-1987. A substantial portion of the collection relates to Ford Foundation policies towards, and activities in, South Africa.
Arrangement
The Office Files of David Bonbright are arranged in two series:
I. Correspondence, 1979-1986 II. Subjects, 1983-1987
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence, 1979-1986; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains incoming and outgoing letters, memoranda and attachments that document Ford Foundation program development, grantmaking, grantee activities and administrative matters throughout Africa, with an emphasis on South Africa. Letters exchanged by Bonbright with South African political figures, leaders of the anti-apartheid movement, Ford Foundation leadership and others concerned with South African social and political conditions illuminate the activities of the Foundation and other philanthropies operating in the region. Collectively, these documents provide a vivid account of the political scene, current events, social and economic conditions, and philanthropic work across the region.
  Arrangement
  The correspondence is arranged chronologically, and is further sorted alphabetically within each year. Letters are filed by the individual recipient’s last name, not by institutional name.
  - 1983-1985 (Box 1 (SK 31085), Folder 1-21)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 2 (SK 31086), Folder 1-15)
- Subjects, 1983-1987; II
  Series contains records related to meetings of the Ford Foundation Board of Trustees held in South Africa during 1982 and 1983, including briefing papers, background readings and grantee information. Also filed here are minutes and related documents of the Study Group on Southern Africa, a regular convening of foundation leaders, NGO staff, academics, political figures and others concerned with international policy towards the apartheid regime in South Africa and regional political issues. Also included are reports on African social and political conditions prepared by the scholar Thomas Karis, the Institute of Current World Affairs, and others organizations.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Association for Guidance and Assistance to Pupils, 1983 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees South Africa Trip, 1982 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 2-3)
  - Board of Trustees South Africa Trip, 1983 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 4-6)
  - Center for Applied Legal Studies, 1982 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 7)
  - Conference in Solidarity with the Liberation Struggles of the Peoples of Southern Africa, 1981-1982 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 8)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs, 1980-1983 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 9)
  - Kairos Theologians, 1985 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 10)
  - Karis, Thomas, 1979-1985 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 11)
  - Labour Monitoring Group, 1984 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous reports, 1979-1985 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 13)
  - Study Group on Southern Africa, 1984-1986 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 14-19)
  - Workshop on Africa, 1985 (Box 3 (SK 31084), Folder 20)
- Appendix A: Reports
  The following list of unpublished reports written by FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers and transferred to the Archives’ collection of staff and consultant reports. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The number on the left is the assigned accession number and may be retrieved via the online catalog.
  - Caughman, Susan. Women at work in Mali: the case of the Markala Cooperative, 1980 November (Report 7016)
  - Farmelo, Laura B. Comparative study of South African and American race relations law and the potential for fostering social change through the legal process in South Africa, 1984 December 21 (Report 12138)
  - Fox, Melvin J. Report on Foundation support of the International African Institute, 1954-1978, 1979 September (Report 4319)
  - Horovitz, Richard A. Southern Africa: international issues and responses: donor agencies, 1981 March (Report 12189)
  - Hyden, Goran. The African crisis and the role of the church, 1985 (Report 12290)
  - Werley, Carolyn. A survey of American private voluntary organization involvement in Sub-Saharan Africa, 1981 February (Report 11915)